Preliminary Guide to the Aleksandr Ivanovich Spiridovitch Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Aleksandr Ivanovich Spiridovitch papers
1890-1950
MS 359
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(27 boxes)
The papers consist of writings and research materials dealing with Russian history, particularly the Romanov dynasty, Rasputin, and the origins of the Russian Revolution. Also included are materials on Peter the Great and the Jews in the Russian revolutionary movement.
Spiridovich, A. I. (Aleksandr Ivanovich), 1873-1952
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Mrs. Nina Spiridovitch in 1962.
Scope and Contents
These papers of General Aleksandr Ivanovich Spiridovitch consist of writings and research materials dealing with Russian history, particularly the origins of the Russian Revolution, and with the Romanov dynasty. Spiridovitch was the organizer and commander of Tsar Nicholas II's imperial bodyguard from 1906 until his retirement in 1916. His memoirs have been published in Russian (Zapiski Zhandarma, [1927?]) and French (Les dernières années de la Cour de Tzarskoie-selo, 1928.), and a draft of the Russian version is included among these papers. Also included are manuscript and typescript drafts of other writings by Spiridovitch, notes, documents, published volumes, scrapbooks of clippings and other printed matter, and lexicographical and biographical materials on many of the people mentioned in the writings.
The papers are only partially processed. English précis of the lexicographical and biographical materials in Boxes 1-2 have been provided.
Biographical / Historical
Aleksandr Spiridovitch was an organizer and commander of Tsar Nicholas II's imperial bodyguard from 1906-1916.
Jews -- Soviet Union; Revolutionaries; Europe; Soviet Union -- History -- Revolution, 1917-1921; Historians; Peter, Emperor of Russia, I, 1672-1725; Rasputin, Grigoriĭ Efimovich, 1869-1916; Spiridovich, A. I. (Aleksandr Ivanovich), 1873-1952
- Inventory, Circa 1890-1950
  - Litsa "A" (Lexicographical and biographical materials: persons A-G.) (Box 1, Folder 1-56)
  - Litsa "D" (Lexicographical and biographical materials: persons I-Z, misc.) (Box 2, Folder 1-36)
  - Khronika tsarstrovania Imperatora Nikolaia II. (The Chronicle of the reign of Emperor Nicholas II.) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Papka Imperatora Nikolaia Vtorogo (Case of documents on life of Nicholas II, his family and the false pretenders of being members of the Tsarist family) (Box 4, Folder 1-13)
  - Khronika biografii Rasputina (The Chronicle of Rasputin's biography) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Poslednie gody Tsarskosel'skogo Dvora Popravki i dopolnenia. (The last years of the court of Tsarskoie Selo. Corrections and additions.) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Materialy i dokumenty k moim vospominamian. (Materials and documents pertaining to my memoirs) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Primechania k istorii partii sotsial-revoliutsionerov i ee predshestuenikoo (Supplementary notes to the history on the party of Social Revolutionaries and their forerunners) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - A.I. Spiridovitch, Revoliutsionnoie dvizherde v Rossii v period imperii, Partia sotsialistov revoliutsionerso u ee predshastoennikov, Vtoroie izdanie, dopolnennoie, Petrograd, 1918. (The revolutionary movement in Russia during the Empire. The Socialist-Revolutionary Party and her forerunner. The Second, enlarged edition. Petrograd, 1918, supplemented by many additional notes in Gen. Spiridovitch's hand.) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Gen. A.I. Spiridovitch, Rasputin, na mashinke sdolavleniami izdano po frantsuski. Po russki ne izdano (Gen. Spiridovitch, Rasputin, typewriter text with additional, published in French, not in Russian.) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Partrety revoliutsionnykh deiatelei po partiam (Portraits of the revolutionary functionaries as classified by the parties) (Box 7)
  - Dokumenty po isltskomi gradonachal'stvu (The Documents on governership of the city of Yalta) (Box 8)
    General
    Also: Lzhe-Anastasia-Chaikovskaia (Pseudo-Anastasia-Chaikovskaia)
  - Olshchestvennoic dvizhenie v Tsarstuovanie Imperatoza Nikolaia Vtorogo, 9 lektsii (The social movements during the reign of Emperor Nicholas the Second, 9 lectures) (Box 9)
  - "Poslednie gody Tsarkosel'skogo Dvora." na mashinke. Tom I. Izdano na franzieskom iazyke. Po russki ne izdano. ("The last years of the Court of Tsarskoie Selo." typewriter manuscript. Vol. I Published in French. Not published in Russian) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Gen. A.I. Spiridovitch, Russkaia litteratura, Pushkin. Zametici. (Russian literature. Pushkin. Notes.) (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
  - Gen. A.I. Spiridovitch, Angliskii perevod knigi, Partia sotsialistov-revoliutsionerov i ee predshestvenniki. Rukopis' (English translation of the book, The Party of Socialist-Revolutionaries and Her Forerunners. Manuscript) (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
  - Papka velikago kniazia Kirilla Yladimirovicha. (The documents-case on Grand Duke Kiril Vladimirovich) (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
  - Materialy k Rasputinu rucmbe M-F [#] (Materials pertaining to book Rasputin. Papers M-F[#]) (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
  - Gen. A.I. Spiridovitch, Poslednie gody Tsarskoie'skogo Dvora, na mashinke, Tom II. Izadano na frantsuskom iszyke. Po russki ne izdano. (The last years of the Court in Tsarskoie Selo," typed manuscript Vol, II. Published in French, Not in Russian) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Materialy k Rasputinu. (Materials pertaining to the book Rasputin ) (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
  - Papka chlenso doma Romanovykh. (The case of documents on members of the House Romanov) (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
  - Materialy k lstarii Bol'shevizma v Rossii. (Materials pertaining to the History of Bolshevism in Russia) (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
  - Istoria revoliutsionnoge dvizhenia v rossii of dekabristov do imperatora Nikolaia II. (The history of Revolutionary movement in Russian from Decembrists until Emperor Nicholas the Second.) (Box 19, Folder 1-12)
  - Le Nouveau Mercure 1717 (Reconstruction of Peter the Great's voyage in France after Le Nouveau Mercure of 1717). (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Bibliografia Piotr Velikii Vo Frantsii v 1717 godu. Bibliography for ( Peter the Great in France in the year 1717 ) (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Peter the Great in Paris, Newspaper clippings. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Piotr Velikii v Parizhe (Peter the Great in Paris) (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Konspekt Asarstuovania Imperatora Nikolaia II. (Synopsis on reign of the Emperor Nicholas II.) (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Illiustratzii k dokladu Piotr Velikii v Parizhe v 1717 godu. (Illustrations for the lecture Peter the Great in Paris in 1717) (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Dokumenty k trudu A.I. Spiridovich, "Piotr Velikii vo Frantsii v 1717 godu." (Documents pertaining to the study by A.I. Spiridovitch: "Peter the Great in France in the year 1717.") (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Piotr Velikii vo Frantsii v 1717 godu. Peter the Great in France in the year 1717 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Kistorii Partii Sotsial-Revoliutsionerov (Material pertaining to the history of the Socialist-Revolutionary Party.) (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Perevorot v Rossii v Fevrale 17-go goda (Upheaval in Russia in Feb. 1917) (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Gerei i tolpa (Heroes and masses) Lecture (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Mliistuo Ministra Stolypina (The Murder of Tsarist Minister Stolypin) (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Rossia i Memtsy (Russia and Germans) Lecture (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Rol'russkoi zhenshchiny v nachem revoliutsionnom diuzhenii. (Participation of women in our revolutionary movement.) (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Angliiski perevod Istorii bol'shevizma v Rossii. (The English translation of the book The History of Bol'shevism in Russia .) (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Gen. Spiridovitch, Podlinnaya rukopis Rasputin. Izdammaya na frantsuskom iszyke. Po russki ne izdana. (Authentic manuscript of the book Rasputin. Published in France. In Russian not published.) (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - 80-ie i 90-ie gody Bumagi Rachkovskogo i Vedomosti i Obsora Departamenta Politsii. (1800 & 1890 Papers of Rachkovski. Records and Survey of the Dept. of Russian Police.) (Box 25, Folder 1-4)
  - Evrei v russkom Revoliutsionnom Dvizhwnii. Evreistvo i fran-masonstvo Protokoly sionskikh Mudretsov. Evreiskii vopros v Rossii v poslednee tsarstvovanie. (The Jews in Russian revolutionary movement. Jewry and Fran-Masonry. Protocols of the Wise men of Zion. The Jewish question in Russia during the reign of Nicholas II.) (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - Politsia, Okhrana i Rozysk. Beloe Dvizhenie. (Police. Criminal Investigation Dept. The movement of Russian White Army.) (Box 27, Folder 1-5)